okay so this is our first solution
raising where we're re-tackling
something we already tackled we did
education and it was more broad on
education um a few months ago
pre-covered 19.
so i wanted the world has changed since
then my life has changed since then and
i wanted to re-tackle education
specifically
for children getting them the foundation
of what they need what do they need
and so um for the first 15 minutes of
course we'll be talking about what it
currently looks like
both in education in general and
specifically during
covid19 and what it looks like the kids
are going back to
a school that's less good than it was
before
right because i don't know so i can't
really speak to that so
because you've been a teacher and you've
got a kid so i'm just going to listen
and take notes if that's okay
feel free to chime in if you yeah
hi yeah yeah eric i know you don't have
um children you don't have children at
school but from when you were
teaching like right now it's funny
because we've been fighting so hard to
get
classroom sizes down so that there's
more one-on-one teacher attention and of
course class sizes are going to have to
be down because of the infrastructure
you can only fit so many kids in
classroom
but they're they're isolated and they're
like they have to follow an even more
regimented rule system
of sit here eat your lunch here don't
play on the playground don't like
it kind of takes all of the social
interaction and joy out of school
what just route memorization right just
this and
it i mean maybe that's not what it's
actually doing but it's what it feels
like it's doing and so
the thought of sending my kid back to do
that
um seems broken and having her home
also even though she doesn't have the
social interaction she has
actually taken um
more of a leap forward in her math and
reading because
even my very inadequate one-on-one
attention
is much better than being lost in the
sea
of children at at school
i'm actually just trying to share
something but it doesn't look like i'll
keep talking
that finding um
let me know when you want me to put it
up right now it looks like a bunch of
files so let me know
yeah it is okay let me just find the one
i'm after
and so like what i want is for her to
learn
reading writing math very very basic
and then i want her to be able to
explore what she wants and what's
what's passionate for her and that's
absolutely not what the school system is
designed for
um it's designed for child care for 12
years
and to teach so that like let's fill
this time it's kind of like the grant
the police defund the police department
they have so much money that they just
spend it it's like well they have so
much time they just fill it full of
information
uh that isn't really sticking in your
brain anyway
and so my focus is very much how do i
get my kid to read write and
have a love of learning at the end of
that still
is it isn't it who's lovable
uh all i see is still the the different
the difference right
okay for some reason i can't seem to
pick one photo and have that as an
option on the screen share i don't know
why anyway whatever never mind
maybe not just nothing but yeah
i i i agree with much of that jubilee i
mean it seems to me that things like
reading and writing and numeracy and so
on
um don't actually need to be taught in
and of themselves right i mean if you if
you can get this love of learning thing
then
you know it won't be very long before a
child runs up against something where
they need to read they need to
understand numbers in order to learn
about this thing they want to learn
about right and so
you know it i do think these things in
the right environment emerge naturally
that the hunger to
learn which unless you stifle it which
is what this picture was about but i
can't seem to put it up for you
oh let me try one more thing hang on if
i
share whole screen just a minute let me
get rid
of this but yeah it seems that our that
our school system is
not about engendering a love of learning
but much more about engendering
a willingness to listen to authority to
obey authority without question to be
fearful
of disability of the consequences of
disobedience right and that
you know this is a very very very old
model i mean it's a model from the 1860s
it's a prussian
model from the 1860s and
you know it was designed to create
docile obedient compliant factory
workers right who who could do the
who were minimally skilled just skilled
enough to do the mundane tasks that were
going to be placed before them but
no more questioning or inquiring than
that right because otherwise
and so you know this is a this is a 150
year old model which was designed
essentially to create autonomous and
factory workers
it's so past its cell by date um
and i mean jubilee this has come up a
couple of times before the and the whole
thing hinges around because the
bavarians came up with this as well i
mean it's been modified subsequently
british universities now have the are
the ones that model the current
um standardized testing but you know the
the whole education system hinges on
learn this get tested on it be able to
regurgitate it well
you get an a and you move on to the next
cog in the wheel kind of thing you know
what i mean and and
it's not possible for every student to
get an a it doesn't matter how well
everybody does the top 15
of them get a's you know what i mean so
it sets people in unhealthy competition
with each other
right from the outset the the the poison
that our education system spreads in the
minds of young people
is and no wonder no wonder more and more
kids of school age are considering or
committing suicide cutting themselves
getting involved in drugs blah blah blah
blah blah blah you know what i mean
depression on the rise
etc etc it is no wonder and i hold
education primarily not entirely not
exclusively but primarily responsible
for
all of that are you
i've heard the name yeah i posted a
video yesterday about the
john taylor gatto because there's a
whole thing in charlotte it's a b about
the schooling and exactly what you said
about the the prussian system of
schooling there's an excellent
documentary called human resources
although it made me cry when i watch it
you know about how it's all about
behaviors and modifying the behaviors of
the children going through the school
system
i.e when they ring the bell that's it up
to something else and as you said
it's about automatons you know what i
mean so um
i don't know how you would actually
go about saving that i don't know i have
i have a i've got a really simple easy
plan which would which would i think
would be incredibly effective
i don't know if jubilee wants to allow
me the time to unpack it because i know
jubilee's heard it a couple of times
before so i don't know if you want to
hear it yeah
but i'd like to i'd like to add it it's
relevant to this part right because what
what
what or maybe to the next part right
when we go into what your vision of the
future is
let's do it do it then i think would be
the most but like right now like we the
school system got put in place exactly
like you said to create factory workers
and
we've fixed some of that right like in
the 80s and 90s they cut out a lot of
the arts program they're putting them
back
in they're realizing that you need to
educate the whole child and so although
there are things that have
are still in place like when i look at
my kids old school they got closed down
at the end of last year
there was a democratic school where we
knew the teachers they came to our house
we had them over for dinner it was
it was peer-to-peer even though they're
older than you and you call them by the
first name and you know
you have a say and you're you're an
important individual versus
even my kids teacher this year is
wonderful
but she's missed so and so and you know
like i call her by one name and she
calls her by another
and i feel less less able to talk to her
like a peer than i did with the other
ones
and now with covid19 all of those
beautiful things that are put in place
are actually even being more eroded that
it's like
more structure and there's a reason for
it theoretically that you know we're
trying to keep people safe
and still have child care and still have
education but it's made it that much
worse so it's like
even if they were looking at things like
taking out standardized testing
like now it's it's well you need to be
apart so how do we keep you in your desk
well
that means kids can't move around kids
can't you know they may have tactile
learning because that shares germs and
i'm like
oh all i want is my and this is the
difference between a few months ago
where i was like well i'm not taking my
kid out of school i need child
care like summer seems so ridiculously
long that i don't have child care for
two months now i've had her home for two
months there's another two and a half
months or two and a half months now
there's another two and a half months to
go
and she's on the ipad all day and and
there are some games that we've
downloaded and some of them are
there's one that was like good for math
monsters or something it's something to
do with monsters
but the reading the reading section they
had was literally just downloaded
picture books like this is not teaching
her how to read and so
i just feel like with all the games that
are out there and all the ways that you
can learn it that there's
ways to find
a catalog like kind of like we talked
about in the last one a catalog of
what's out there
and like where how do i get my kid to
learn math and how do i get my kids
learn reading if ten thousand parents
came together
well i'm getting all over the place then
we could we would have buying power
right we'd have the ability to create
one where it's not
50 bucks a month it's not for for all of
the material but if it's 50 bucks a
month that's way cheaper than private
education
like to actually create something that's
like gets my kid her
very basic skills and then lets her
explore
explore the rest and i again mush them
all together
so we can go on to the next part if you
want
and share our beautiful vision of the
future what we would like it to look
like
whether that's so eric this is perfect
and i'll let you
go on even if it takes the 15 minutes
yeah i'm still trying to do this
screenshot i'm going to try one more
time
uh what do you think i'm going to do so
when you do screen share up at the top
it'll say your entire screen application
window
vine says chrome window and you can pick
which one
so there we go and then if i do
that can you now see it yeah i see
something
indoctrination because when something is
true and correct it must be hammered
into the brains of defenseless children
yes
mine is the uh let's get that that's
where it starts to do that
many mirrors in one so yeah i mean
i i what you were saying before jubilee
about educating the whole child though
you're right there was some progress
towards reintroducing
drama and um excuse me art and music
and crafts and all of this and cooking
and and all of this kind of stuff there
was some move to do that but
even when that was going on it was still
you know in your 50 lessons a week or
whatever it is
you know you have five math five science
five english you know three geography
three history whatever it might be
and the odd one here and there of you
know what i mean
and every child did the same thing it's
still not educating the whole child
because there's no flexibility as to
what are the needs of this child versus
that child you know
you know emphasize this for that child
and de-emphasize that for that child you
know what i mean there's
there's none of that in the in the
education system so
and and it all hinges i keep coming back
to it all hinges on the need for
comparison of school with school of
student with student of teacher with
teacher
and this all comes about through
standardized testing right standardized
because
if every child sits the same test then
you you know you can compare very easily
this child's performance with that
child's performance all this school
performs with that school's performance
but a
it's not fair because all schools are
not situated in the same place and have
the same kind of kids going to them and
blah blah blah
but b it means that exactly what i just
said the entire curriculum ends up being
completely prescribed every single child
is on a treadmill doing exactly the same
thing
being evaluated in exactly the same way
according to exactly the same parameters
exactly the same standards generally
where is the where is the individuality
in this so
removing standardized testing i think is
a pretty easy matter i mean it rests on
the premise that
most people broadly agree with what i'm
talking about right most people feel
that the standardization but they can't
just say well i'm not going to let my
kids sit any tests right because then
their kid doesn't get a levels can't go
to university you know has a whole
bunch of doors closed to them so what
you do is you do a jubilee
you say right we're going to try and
abolish standardized testing by getting
a million people to sign up to agreeing
to withdraw their children from
all standardized tests to advocate for
an end to standardized test to vote for
politicians who advocate for an end of
standardized
to advocate with other parents to remove
their children and once a million people
have
have all made this commitment then the
thing is activated and
everybody starts doing it at the same
time right and so you remove the whole
well what can i do on my own well you're
not on your own you're with a million
other people doing exactly the same
thing at exactly the same time there's
enormous strength in numbers
and so it deleverages the powerlessness
that the individual feels right it
allows lots of individuals to act as
one and if a million people take their
kids out of standardized testing
um and say we're not doing it
and we're we're going to encourage
everybody else to not do it
then at the very least you've created
the space for a serious conversation
around standardized testing to happen
and i think it's pretty easy all you've
got to do is create a secure database
right an encrypted database where people
can sign up
anonymously and then when the threshold
is reached
it becomes transparent it opens up and
everything is transparent and everybody
begins acting on their commitment so can
i invite
that your beautiful version of the
future is that's possible and it's
happened so a million people have signed
up
and they've signed up to not have
standardized testing now what does
education look like
who knows who knows now you have now you
have an opportunity to have a discussion
of what we
actually want education to do what we
want it to look like how much of it is
you know if what we want is child care
so that both parents can go to work
every day then let's say that let's be
explicit about it and set it up to be
child care right and not this sham
education if we want it to actually
educate then we need to think about what
is an education
and you know what role does school play
in that because school is not the only
place you go to get educated right you
get educated at home you get educated by
your friends you get educated every time
you turn on the tv or the internet or
whatever right all of this
feeds into your education and so you
know that
until we have a wide-ranging
broad reaching conversation about what
this
actually means what does the word
actually mean what do we actually want
from it
as a society or as a community do we
wish to organize it
at a society-wide level or do we wish to
organize it in a more nuclear level
right and at a much more local level
you know allocate funding to a group of
households right there you go
figure out schooling for yourselves
whatever you know what i mean there are
a million different possibilities
we need to have a conversation i'm not
going to try and pretend i've got
the solutions to all of these problems
right that would that would be absurd
but
we absolutely need to have the space to
have a conversation which means
kicking out this poisonous
structure of standardized testing
which i have to say although i have been
more critical of your idea in the past
um i absolutely think that that is that
is
a road forward however i also think just
like covid19 has been um
instrumental in moving ubi forward i
think it might also be instrumental in
moving forward not necessarily let's not
have standardized testing
but how do i get my kid educated
right not how do i send them to school
and get them educated all i care about
is her
right how do i get her to understand the
fundamentals of information that she
needs
and love learning and get there and so
my version of a beautiful future
changed from a few months ago where i
would love to live rurally with people
who are working on technology game b
projects we're growing our own food and
part of that is also
um having the basics taught honestly on
an ipad through games
and through you know 20 minutes on math
20 minutes on reading
and then having a bunch of other adults
who are also present
um as mentors for things you're
interested in right if you want to learn
to bake bread
right they're baking bread at this time
it's not you know school from nine to
three
it's hey baking i'm baking bread on
wednesday who wants to come and do it
there's six spots
i'm you know i'm gonna go out for a
nature walk who wants to come and look
for that and it's not
structured classes it's does it interest
you does it spark your interest
and i think that also meets like there's
this idea that because kids are on ipads
all the time
school isn't entertaining enough for
them and therefore the kids are broken
i'm like well why can't we make school
more entertaining like why they're on
the ipad learning i can tell you all the
things my kids learned through
don't you see how none of that can come
about while the need for testing is
there
well no because what i'm saying is uh
standardized testing i should say i've
got actually no problem with testing
it's the standardized
model but since my worries for my kid if
yeah you're right if my kid was an
engineer or a doctor then i could see
that there's a big problem
in that in that i want her to be able to
get into university
uh if you want your kid to be an
entrepreneur to be a and
to be an inventor to be literally
anything that it can be
from the inside and as long as i'm as
long as i could find 10
000 other people to create these things
with we don't need to care
about everyone else and then if we
create something that we are not doing
standardized testing
and invites people and i mean i'm
surrounded by people who don't do
standardized tests but what about the
volvo
kids out of that what about the vast
majority of kids who have no
idea what they want to do until they're
in their 20s or whatever do you know
what i mean why
why do we need to channel them down
these routes you know you must select
from sciences or humanities when you're
14 or whatever you know what i mean and
and stuff why not do that to them again
it all comes down to
you've got to fit into this structure so
that you can be evaluated so that we can
decide which
next thing you're going to move on to do
you know what i mean it is absolutely
central to the whole thing what you were
talking about before about a mentorship
program
being a big part of the education system
right and so i want to find out about
cook bread making is an excellent
example
i want to find out about bread making
and you go to a catalog and you find out
people in your local area who are doing
bread making and you ring them up and
say i want to come and do bread making
great comment you know what i mean
and it just sorts itself out amongst
providers and wanters and people who are
wanting to go and learn about bread
making are themselves teaching guitar to
some other people or whatever you know
what i mean and
and it all goes around in a great big
beautiful circle sorry kerry you want to
speak
i'd say just um first i was i was just
when i was at school i was in the third
eyes level of classes
and because i wanted to do art and
design i got put into the bottom
because i wanted to do that you know
what i mean because
at a certain age you have to get choose
choose what you want
you don't know what i want you know i
mean but because you like doing
something
then you get thrown into the bottom
classes because like i wanted to do art
so i got thrown in the bottom you know
you must be stupid if you're an artist
you must be stupid yeah i mean this is a
quite widely prevalent attitude in the
education system because intelligence
again
because intelligence is defined by your
performance in standardized tests right
this is
primarily what defines your level of
intelligence and so
you know any other kind of intelligence
and there are many many of them right
are simply disregarded as being not of
value right unless you have
this particular kind of intelligence
then you're then you're not intelligent
right it's it's it's so it's so
poisonous i can't even begin to
articulate how
awful it is what what a what a
destructive force it is in our culture
have you had a look at the finland model
of education i have yes i'm somewhat
familiar i mean
i'm certainly no expert but i'm somewhat
familiar with it and they rely on
testing not at all right they do one
final exam at the age of 18 i think the
university entrance
and that's it there's no homework they
have fewer hours a week at school a week
at school that we do
it's all based on collaboration rather
than competition you know the whole
thing is is
and they have the best outcomes anywhere
of anywhere in the world right so
and there are other things there's the
kipp school program in the us where they
take where they whether
they open up schools in inner city
primarily black
locations right and you know throughout
the edge throughout the history of
education i'm sorry i'm waffling on but
i'm really passionate about it
there has always been this thing where
children from deprived areas be they
black or not doesn't matter it's it's
it's it's economically deprived areas
never ever keep up with their peers from
more economically advantaged there is
right their educational outcomes are
always always
always consistently on average of course
there's exceptions right but
on average are consistently a grade
grade and a half below
those of the from the and it was thought
that this gap was unbridgeable but these
kipp schools have come into inner city
taken the most deprived children
and turned them into the highest
performance some of the highest
performing children in the country you
know what i mean so the the
the methodology and the process that we
use
to educate children is way way way more
important than the
background or the social um
um whatever you know what i'm trying to
say that the children come from
um so yeah and these things exist in the
world but they are not
taken up and again i've had this
conversation with jubilee a few times
before these solutions
to many of these or potential solutions
yeah attractive promising
lines of lines of progression to these
things exist in the world already but
they are not followed because to be
followed on mass
requires governments to fund them right
and governments don't fund because they
don't give governments what they want
from education
which is as i said before a compliant
docile obedient population
so you know again even beyond
standardized testing
we need to get rid of central
governments right who are creating
education policy because while they
insist on
keeping a tight hold on education policy
then it's going to remain centralized
standardized you know what i mean what
else can it be
if the government wishes to retain
control over it right
so i think you're going to be up against
all the universities because you know
the way they get their funding and that
they've got to
jump to the tune whoever's setting all
this yeah they're rackets now
universities businesses that
um fund universities
they're all like well you know we want
these workers you must give us that
because you've only got to look at the
rockefeller
foundation on the rest of them so unless
unless you start coming up with a
blueprint
a blueprint that people may be
interested or design of what what it
would like in the future have a
blueprint
and then from that blueprint gather
people together
to have a look at it design it and pull
it apart until you know
and to and then
i mean there are incredible people out
there who have run experiments you know
what i mean at decent scales and
things that work you know what i mean
they just need to be rolled out you need
you need your children about gathering
all those people together who have done
it then
and starting from there would that not
work
starting from because if you get it here
it's it's a little early i'm going um
because i would love to get your guys's
i want to actually get something like
solve something here because it's
actually something i really need in my
life
that instead of focusing on this is all
of what solution right scene is right
instead of focusing on what can we
uh make governments do because that
would be great but i don't know that's a
lot of work
um i am one parent who's willing to not
have my kid do standardized testing
i'm one parent who's focused on her joy
her learning
and if i had 9999 other families
all who wanted to do that right that
they don't want to send their kid to
public school
they can't afford private school
what could education look like for ten
dollars a month for my kid
with an ipad with other people whether
i'm
going around the world whether i'm stuck
in my house whether i'm living rurally
what could we bring in so that um
it doesn't matter how i mean how much or
how little money you have
because there could always be
scholarships for that 10 a month what
could we do with 10 000 people
to create a foundation of learning
that sparks joy for the kid that
isn't reliant on on necessarily having a
teacher that's making fifty thousand
dollars a year as much as i want
teachers to make money
that that's not necessarily the central
focus my central focus on how do i get
my kid to learn the basics
and still have a love of learning that
would cost ten dollars a month or less
i reckon you could create i mean again
it's more work than it is money but it
would require some money and ten dollars
ten dollars a month or ten dollar fee
per participant is probably around about
the ballpark so
what i'm thinking of is a homeschooling
network
right where those 10 000 families
are part of a homeschooling network and
within that pool of 10 000 people
you have the skills and resources to
educate
all of the children in those 10 000
families right so it's a
self-sustaining unit and so you know i
know i i know you
you struggle with um physical work right
and sustain periods of activity jubilee
right but
but nevertheless even with those
constraints that you have i dare say you
would find
something that you could offer by way of
part of the educational program where
you know for half an hour a week or
something you could have
three or four kids and take them out
looking at flowers or whatever it is
that you might be into that you
contribute you know what i mean
and and you know everybody not everybody
right but if the majority
of the people the majority of the time
within this within this collection of
ten thousand have
things to offer and you remove the
constraint
you remove the shackles from the
children right you know what i mean
there's going to be no exams no tests
whatever but
there's all this available to you right
and then the parents are participating
they're learning with the children as
well
because they're as their children
explore avenues a lot of that stuff we
stuff the parents have never learned
about as well right so there's going to
be this
this whole i don't know just just
group of 10 000 households learning and
teaching
each other you know what i mean and i i
i know it's a bit of a utopian vision
but i see no reason why
it couldn't work and it could be part
online part in people's living rooms
part in the park
you know what i mean park walking around
old churches what it whatever it might
be i mean there's an and and it can be
tailored and it can be constantly
changing and it can be alive
and the kids can participate in this
development and creation and and
and the whole you know and it's proper
education for everybody
i had an idea one was not an idea but my
friend she homeschooled their kids
and their kids are lovely you know i
mean so maybe
starting with the people who are already
doing them schooling
and then finding out what's out there
what they are but also
you know the parents like some parents
may feel like they haven't got their
intelligence or whatever to homeschool
the kids so they don't
you know i mean so i think you'd you'd
probably need
the the for the kids as well as the
parents as well you know i mean so it
would be so
need to be something there for them as
well but in order to spark joy
and not i don't i don't know how you do
that in kids because i don't have any so
i can't speak from that experience say
but i know
you know i used to i used to go i wasn't
lost
yeah yeah because i was put into a
school
when i was about 10 or 11 and i love
dinosaurs that's all i wanted to do was
dinosaurs right
and the headmaster told me mum to take
me out to school because i wouldn't
learn anything there
you know i mean because i because she
said oh you know i was too intelligent
from what they were trying to teach me
and so i i got put you know out of that
school you know when that was in a poor
deprived area of the liverpool aid and
toxic
so um but yeah but as i said that's all
i wanted to do that in greek mythology
that was all a love day but obviously
you know when you go to school and you'd
have to do all these other things that
you don't want
you're not because nobody ever shows you
hey when you go and do maths nobody ever
shows you the practical applications you
you're
supposed to just learn it like i've had
it you know what i mean your times table
let it like a product live it like a
part of it you know what i mean so
there is some value to it to be honest i
mean my the fact that i know my
timestamps without having to think about
it is just an
automatic reflex response it's actually
kind of useful i mean you know maybe
there's better ways of learning it but
i'm i'm not ungrateful for the fact that
i stood up every morning for two years
or whatever it was
and recited my times tables with the
rest of the class you know it works
and i also know my times table in fact
you want to know how i learned my times
tables
schoolhouse rock 369
12 15 18 21 24
27 30. it's still in there
and i think that there's ways right
music through play that that you
actually can learn those things it's
also how i know that
the continent is is through like a rhyme
from when i was
i think in grade two but i actually
don't think that's pie in the sky
idea eric i think having it's funny
because my ver
like my life has changed right so before
i was like i need my kid in school eight
hours a day so i can concentrate on what
i'm doing
to save the world my health all of these
things
no now she's home she's doing it what i
need is for her to
not be bored all day although gordon's a
great sparker too
there's something because it doesn't
even need to be parents right if we have
this if it was ten thousand parents
putting in ten dollars a month
but anyone could volunteer to teach a
class if you like dinosaurs
would you rather teach a class to a
bunch of kids who don't care about
dinosaurs or the ones who
really care about dinosaurs the ones you
really wanted you know i mean yeah and
so i think there would be enough people
it's so sad what you said because the
thing is if you've been allowed to just
you know explore dinosaurs and explore
greek mythology i mean sooner or later
in greek mythology you're going to come
and get up against diogenes and
pythagoras and
episodes and you know these kinds of
people and you're going to right okay
well what were these people talking
about and you're going to need to learn
math so that to understand what the
they were talking about and
you know it comes on its own if you just
let people
oh yeah it comes you know what i mean
sooner or later they go i need to know
about this and then they
and then they want to and then they're
easy to teach right
yeah yeah so i suppose he's just
developing paths for them to follow and
isn't there but allowing them paths to
be part of us
a bigger thing pathways just not
blocking pathways
that's all you've got to do you know
where how do you instill a joy of
learning in kids you don't instill a joy
of learning you just don't
squash it out of them you know
well have a look that's john taylor
because even you think he
he tried to do something similar for the
education
in the maybe the 70s and that whereas
he'd just get kids to to come to him and
i think one of the
the examples that he'd given this kid
he was getting thrown out of school
nobody wanted to have anything to do
with them
and he said right go to that um museum
go go there and tell me all the stuff
and it the kid could
come back to the education system
because there was stuff that he wanted
to do there
rather than getting you know everyone
gets failured into sort of like
these little troughs and then as they
get into the little trots then
and then people turn into silos and they
only got these people
who don't speak to her because you don't
transcend all the different groups you
not really just stay in their own little
corner
and then that's them for the rest of
their life but i do think there's
something in the terms
of like businesses the way businesses
are operating
and how they are because they're the
ones who are giving all the universities
the money to chain out
you know what i mean and obviously that
goes back and back and back as well
so i think if you come up come at it
with the top
bottom up approach but you'd also need
to sort of like tackle the
the top and maybe get maybe people who
are interested in game b to maybe
infiltrate their maybe start so because
my very the thing about game day is what
i'm noticing
as i said it's all about transcendence
including and it's all about
building something that the corporates
and all the other people and the
business sector
will start coming and saying teach us
how to do this you know what i mean
teach us how to do this in that way you
know so therefore that will change it
once you start getting in there buttons
until that's why it goes back to
blueprints just blueprints of ideas of
what could be
like your solution raising than this but
they need to be yeah let's work on a
little blueprint
show it to the other people see what
they think add transcend and include you
know what i mean so
but that's what i'm thinking that's some
fun topic again
this is the one i actually i'm like
let's just grab solution raising for
this
like i actually want to have a
conversation about not how we
create 10 000 an education how do i get
10 000 people to have that how do i have
100 parents have that conversation
because we're actually in this right by
september
i'm either sending my kid back to the
school where she learns to read and
write
or i have something else in place so
that i don't feel like it's all on me
and my kid's not gonna learn to read and
write
because it's all on me um or i
why don't you make this your thing for
your process raising why don't you make
this your
your um you know your what's it called
guinea pig there you go for the for the
process raising yeah
so how do i actually then so much the
better but in the meantime you know
you're talking about something that you
actually care about in the meantime
can i ask you um because i was thinking
you know like certainly found out about
the trivium
and the quadrillion not so long ago and
i'm like why aren't you teaching that in
schools from an early age
what are your thoughts on that i don't
actually know what you're talking about
trivium and quad review
right okay um i need to i can't i'm sure
to explain and i
have all these ideas i've actually
clapped with china so
oh okay then maybe you need to go look
at that bit more where's that from is
that zack stein
no i came across it ages ago the tribune
and the chord jbm it's all about
rhetoric logic and
my thing about not being taught in
school nobody teaches you about money
nobody teaches you about you know from a
young girl because if you understood
money you're not going to be a nice
compliant doctor you're going to be
outraged you know what i mean
what the is this what what are you
doing what is wrong with you how on
earth
are we running society on this ponzi
scheme seriously
this is why this is why kids don't learn
about you know the
the economics that's taught is this
abstract
university first because i blow that up
sorry
again maybe you need to be in university
first before they blow that up
i'm sorry you know what i listened to
the chancellor of the exchequer in the
uk talking about you know
living within our means and balancing
the budget and paying off the debt and
you clearly don't understand how money
works it is impossible
it is impossible to do these things you
cannot live within your means
under an ever expanding money supply
that has to expand forever in order to
pay the interest which otherwise cannot
be covered
you know what i mean that the the the it
is
by any definition it's a ponzi scheme
right an aries
society is built on this foundation on
this quicksand
okay sorry no no no that's not i'm just
like excited
so like i said i'm ruining this solution
raising because i think there's
something else that's like here
and i'm about to start a fire so if
somebody can
could help me start that fire and keep
it going that because it
is like i said because of cobid 19 this
thing has changed from being fringe
right families who i'm in with right
like i got the fringe families
who i could probably find a thousand of
them but finding
people who already homeschooled people
who unschool and people who
this is the first year they might
consider doing that
actually getting them together on a zoom
call and doing solution raising for
education
in you know like having 100 of them and
having let's see what comes out let's
have a note taker let's do that
um but on the fire starter
i don't know how to actually like i i
can write that up and get i'm pretty
sure i get 100 people do a zoom call
i can't do the stuff that comes after
that i can't i can
break us up we can have the conversation
whatever chaos happens is awesome
but then how do people submit their idea
how do we work through
and i and this is process raising but
like
i want something by september just by
september
or like you know what i mean let's go by
september 2021
i want something that my kid can use
from anywhere in the world
on an ipad right that's that's maybe
that's not the focus that comes out
that's the other thing that was the
other thing i just wanted to push back a
little bit not that ipads don't have
their place for sure they do but i don't
think i don't think reliance 100
on ipad content there's got to be a
place
for actual in-room person-to-person
small groups or even larger groups of
kids actually doing stuff together
in you know in reality as well i mean
as well they and so this ten thousand
people can be somewhat scattered right
they can
because a lot of it is online and so
they can be somewhat scattered but
they also need to cluster to some degree
so that you know three or four kids can
go around to someone else's house and do
something together
right you know play a game or explo or
you know look at flowers or
learn about dinosaurs or bake bread or
whatever it might be
actually do stuff together the
difference
is only that covid19 has made it so that
all those beautiful things in person
have become that
like not gonna last yeah it's not gonna
last forever so that that is gonna you
know hopefully not
but it also might change like this might
be our first pandemic like we don't know
what the future holds
just true if you could do with an ipad
right and then i think it automatically
comes out that yeah of course i want to
know who my neighbors are so i can
coordinate with them because yes
i don't want to be the one to take my
kids to the park i want some you know
what i mean i want to go with 10 kids i
want to know
i think it's easier to um
substitute real life stuff for ipad when
the need arises than it is
to do everything on ipad and then assume
that people will also do stuff in real
space i don't think it works like that i
i i think that yeah i feel the real
space ought to be
more foundation like i said if the need
arises then you can you know you can
figure out ways to do that stuff
more online or just abandon it right
because remember there's no outcomes
being measured at the end of all this
right it's just about educating kids and
so if it needs to go on hold and make
other arrangements for a while and and
improvise and wing it
well you know you've got the freedom to
do that no one's looking over your
shoulder telling you've got to do
something different you know this is the
whole beauty of it
you can just do what you think is best
given the circumstances as they present
themselves
you know this is this yeah that that
freedom has to be
i'm i'm also kind of quite excited about
this idea because
as kerry said there are plenty of people
out there who are already doing
homeschooling so if you can repeat
those and you know but as she also quite
rightly said there's
if you're going to homeschool your kids
in the current environment they are
still required to sit tests right and so
you still have to comply
with government legislation where if
there's 10 000 of you doing it or
even god bless more than that right but
if there's if there's a lot
and it is a self-contained thing you can
just you know what we're not doing
any of that and you know you can come
and knock on our doors and send us fine
notices and we're just going to
ignore you
off we're doing the best for our
kids i i suppose what it comes down to
at the end of the day
you don't want to be doing stuff that
you think might noble or hobble
your kids future right in terms of those
like how to get jobs how are they going
to get
their future of going to university
racking up seventy thousand dollars
worth of debt so they can't get the job
afterwards
wouldn't want to jeopardize that future
no no no but like if you look at the
metrics and the way people get
employed for doing jobs and not
you know i mean you've got to oh do you
have a degree no sorry
you know i mean you have this no sorry
yeah
but you know what if you actually if
you've got relationships that you've
built in your life
and you've got capabilities and you're
together kind of per you'll
find stuff to do in this world you know
i mean you will much more so than
if you've got some piece of paper saying
you've got a degree but you're otherwise
useless which is the case with a
lot of university graduates right
you know no wonder they can't find jobs
because they haven't got a clue
how to do anything
they're 25 years old never done a
goddamn thing but they got a hundred
thousand dollars worth of debt which
they got to pay off
and so now they're working in mcdonald's
because what else can they do
it was funny when i was working in
starbucks people used to just come to me
and you know
the way people look at you and they used
to think everybody working behind the
counter
was sick and they were all sort of like
studying genetics and this and that you
know what i mean
so yeah the whole thing is so deeply
broken i mean it's actually kind of
laughable in a way if it wasn't that so
many people were suffering it would be
funny
yeah and i mean i have no faith that
what exists today is existing in 20
years or even if it does that that is in
the best interest of my child
like that even if it's an uber
competitive she needs to get a job world
i can see that that is the world we live
in right now and i see people who've
been through homeschooling and
unschooling
who are just better prepared because
they like have a sense of themselves and
a sense that they can learn stuff
even though they suck at grammar and
spelling you know what i mean like
there's something they foundationally
don't have
but there's something that
foundationally do and so finding 10 000
parents or families
that are more in my position of like i
don't want i don't care
i don't care if the world is competitive
i don't need my kid to be employed she
will be employing other people
she will be an entrepreneur she will be
an artist she will like there's so many
ways to figure out
how to get your needs back she'll figure
out how to make get her needs met with
ten thousand other people
right absolutely absolutely
it's it's that confidence in yourself
that you can figure out right and
that you can learn what you need to
learn in order to figure out and
that you can
form useful and productive and
meaningful relationships with people in
order to accomplish
shared goals you know what i mean all of
this kind of stuff if you've got that
then you know your your paper
credentials are
irrelevant next to that they really are
it's not to say they're not a nice thing
to have in addition but give me one or
the other and i'll take thing number one
every single time
okay i feel there's 10 000 people
in vancouver who are in my
circle or three circles removed easy
how many were there three million people
in vancouver four million people said no
yeah
two or three no no no because you do
understand that if 10 000 people take
themselves out of the vancouver school
system or
the bigger range right and they're like
oh yeah no this isn't going to work for
us we're doing it here
then yeah you have 10 000 people to be
like our funding isn't going here it's
going here
but that's not the purpose right the
purpose is like we're putting in 10
a month whatever they give us awesome
but then we have cloud as well but um
yeah
yeah listen if they give you funding
great but you're not you don't need it
right you're not dependent on it this is
the thing if they give it to you then
great then you can
buy some equipment or sports outfits or
whatever you know what i mean i'm sure
you can find
good ways to spend it if they give it to
you but you're not requiring it you're
not dependent on it and in fact in the
meantime
if they don't want to give you any of
the money that you've paid in taxes back
then they've got that bit more to spend
on everybody else you know what i mean
who's still in there who's still in the
other system
so yeah it's a whatever it's a win-win
right
like last year when her school closed
down i had this beautiful vision of all
because she was
i was telling her how school worked so
she's like well that's the first thing
to go
and i'll be discussing that i was like
oh sweetie that's not how your new
school works right like you can't
like we'll be bringing stuffed animals
like we'll be protesting them is like
envisioning all these little democratic
skins
kids going to school and starting a like
revolution right
that is kind of what's like it's like
the parents of okay we're going to pull
our kids out and we're going to make
something for you
but there's something here that is
huge and it doesn't need to be as well
it'd be so much fun to do i mean imagine
how much fun it would be
for those that participated in it it
would be it would it would be it would
be a hoot it would be
trailblazing it would be it would be an
adventure it would be a
constant i mean it might be a bit
overwhelming at times and it might be a
bit
even frightening possibly at times but
only because it's unknown right and
you don't we're used to knowing where
things are going right we know that at
the end of this year she's going to sit
a test and then she's going to go up
tonight i mean this is another thing
right
it and again it comes back to
standardized testing this thing of
moving children
on one year every year just because the
calendar
goes around once right irrespective of
what they have or haven't accomplished
during the course of that year
it's it's it's ridiculous and you don't
get any cross-mixing of ages in school
right everybody's kept together with
people who are you know plus or minus
six months their age whatever and
and so again it's it's so restrictive
and it's
and but but again at the end of every
year there's a test that you do
and blood let lead learn that moves you
onto that you know what i mean it's it's
it's all oh it's such a horror it's such
a worry it's like
it's like i'm it's like i'm having a
nightmare and at some point i'm gonna
wake up
you know those nightmares where you know
it's a nightmare and you can wake up
sort of voluntarily from them right
yeah except i can't actually seem to get
myself awake from this one
but there's some like you know because i
love it you've got
um you know a lot of people in vancouver
how about starting with them
so they're saying right okay so ooh
gathering all the parents
okay look let me let me couch it this
way for you do you know seven people
who'd be willing to meet up and discuss
the idea of that just for that
absolutely tomorrow
yeah we'll start with them or do you
want me to yeah
five iterations of that five iterations
of that you've got 10 000 people it's
incredible isn't it
this is well as i said this is why i've
got some money yesterday because
i could see how it all worked to me but
i'm a bit explaining it
but yeah so if you've got seven people
who you're gonna host a conversation
with
and talk about this and and people from
the home right
and then see what's out there in
vancouver see what's getting done in
vancouver in terms of homeschooling
have a look at the government department
see what the education department
go through the lot see what's there
already and then get the seven
and to have a look at all of that so
obviously you need someone to help do
research with
finding about or about every set of
educational
things in vancouver yeah i don't know so
here's the thing i don't actually care
what vancouver's doing and i don't care
but i bet you're in the game i care
i want to create something for aurora
right and i want other people
somewhere if you put a post up in game b
especially as seeing as how you're an
admin or a model whatever it is you are
um if you put a post up saying is there
anyone
in vancouver ideally otherwise in canada
because i would imagine the rules are
broadly the same province to province i
mean
there'll be differences but broadly the
same um who homeschools their child if
so i'd really like to talk to you right
and
and i guarantee you you'll get you'll
get a couple of people who are
homeschooling their kids
oh i know i i'm part of the bc's
homeschoolers and unschoolers
oh right okay great i have the test
foundation i'm telling you i can get a
hundred people to this meeting tomorrow
right i don't know if it's the one thing
do it baby
yeah and so having a zoom call that we
actually but it needs to be and then
what do they go
do solution raisings in their small
group and then what did you come up with
that you could do with 10 000 people and
a month and then which one's the best
and how do we like actually go through
a chaotic process phrasing it creates
something
well you could just make a proposition
at the start right a fairly open
proposition i've gathered you all
together because i'm interested
in particularly for my own daughters but
also more broadly creating
a homeschooling network with
a bunch of people so that we can
collectively between us educate all of
our kids
you know and and i brought you together
to discuss that right and so you're not
leaving it completely open you've
already
given the and then and then see what
people come up with hey do they like the
idea in general and if so what sort of
stuff do they come up with and
and so it should be productive from
minute one i think within that within
that sort of loose frame
but the issue is you can't have a
conversation with a hundred people right
so you need to break them into groups
and then like does that group look like
pick seven pick seven or even
pick right pick three people that's a
good point start with five or six or
seven or whatever
even if you just pick three of people
three people
right three people who you trust there's
a relationship there
pick those three and then speak to them
and then do you know anybody else you'd
be interested and then
actually as you're having a conversation
with them three take down the notes of
what you did
what what specifically what's the what
do they get frustrated at
what do they think is not working then
make a note of what what they think is
not working at the moment
and what they would like right so those
three so even if you do it three at a
time
we maybe don't know each other and then
start and then but it has to be from the
ground and i think it does
you know you can do on zoom on that but
there's a period of time when it's going
to need face to face because you're
going to need to
establish those relationships right in
order for them because they if they feel
they shush
you know you can figure all that out as
you go but kerry is right i like that
three or four people
just get them together have a comp and
just see what happens from there right
who do they know um you know where do
they live how could you get together in
real you know actual face-to-face
you know what are their kids like what
you know what do they like and not like
and and and just just just just let it
emerge and see what happens
oh god i wish i was there and i wish i
had kids so i could get involved in this
this is this is this sounds like fun
right but that that's what you do
jubilee right that's that's what i've
been kind of
beating me up for everything you know
what i mean it's just like i'm happy to
sleep
with a bit of math science tuition
online by the way if it's in any way
anyway anyway needed at any time i'd be
very happy to chip in
with like not just people who are home
getting the kids skilled and that but
the actual teachers in the vancouver
area
pick three teachers you you know get
together
together with the three get together
with the three teachers that you know
three parents that you know okay do it
separate teachers parents
right because you might not be seeing it
from a perspective the day of
and find out all their frustrations with
the system that's going on
yeah that's a good point another
excellent point yeah
yeah i like your name instead you're
quite friendly with
one of the teachers at your daughter's
school right jubilee you said you won't
know
like her previously she said you were
quite friendly with i'm pretty sure i
think there's
three teachers at cohousing i know her
previous school
i have her like yeah her the principal
the person
one of my favorite people at co-hosting
was instrumental in helping windsor
house get started and she knows the
the test system excellent perfect
perfect
so you've got you've i mean you're ready
you're ready to get rolling aren't you
jubilee i mean you've got a couple of
small groups that you could get talking
to straight away you're ready to get
rolling
i just i don't know how you go from
small to big it's like i want 10 000 and
what infrastructure do we need
to play yeah forget about exactly forget
about that for now just
just take the first step and see what
happens
the three right three teachers three
parents right take those two groups
get to know them build it but have
conversation each week get to know what
what they're talking about each week
ideas on that will emerge from the group
who's
able to do the stuff that you can't do
right and
all of it whatever whatever you know
i don't do homework harry now you just
canceled it before that
no
jubilee i'd be happy to i'd be happy to
come along as well if you would if you
would like me there i'd be happy to come
along
i know i'm not listening to a this is a
small group i think
putting it in a zoom and then saying
like making a document that's just like
their basics of what this is
creating a zoom if three people show up
awesome if 100 people show up awesome
putting them in smaller groups to
discuss exactly what you said what don't
you like about it what are your family's
needs
and i like you know his idea of picking
three that you know
and trust just to just as a seminal
group right
i just i can't even pick and choose them
like i'm like well then
just pick three right i mean just just
pick three if you can't pick the best
three then just just just pick three at
random if necessary throw a dice
whatever whatever suits your process
i quite like dice for selections like
that where i can't really you know what
where there's no
way to make an informed choice right but
you have to make a choice and so
yeah i like the dive my issue so we have
three and then how where what do we do
from that conversation
but i deeply trust and i think you do
too i deeply trust
that it will come right if you if you
pursue something
earnestly and you find people who share
your earnest desire to
pursue this thing then what you need
will
what you need will come as you need it
kind of thing right
i i i i do believe that i mean i don't
necessarily think it's a woo
thing i think it may be whatever
whatever
i it does seem it does seem that that's
how it works and so yeah you station you
begin developing relationship
in in in the course of having this
conversation and then during that
conversation the next step
will be determined right we'll be
discussed and hammered out and and that
will be the next step whatever it is
which
will then lead to the next step being
formulated at that stage and
and and so on and yeah i
just as i say happy to participate in
any way that you want me to just ask
subject to availability
right pixie people i'm excited there's
some fire starting
can i literally just do the sparks it
sounds like
one of your people would be this person
in your cohort i got the sense it was a
she although i don't think you said she
is she
yes both actually one of whom is a
teacher
right okay and the other one who helps
open or help get
she helped yeah open windsor house her
son went there and her grandkids
went there until it closed down her
daughter was like one of the
was the secretary until she had got in a
car accident like she's
so yeah find one from the um
homeschooling or unschooling or whatever
it is is group
and there you go that's your first
that's your first quorum
of three four's a perfect number on zoom
right
and yeah
coordinate i literally don't how it is
like the issue with it being
with being the person who was
instrumental in creating it she doesn't
have kids she has grandkids but she does
you know what i mean like her
grandkids she's got you know grandkids
loves the grandkids
she's got skin in the game skin in the
game so she's got that
right so whether she's got kids but
she's got grandkids
right okay we've all got skin in the
game even if we don't have kids we've
still got skin in the game i mean an
education system benefits
all of us right whether we have kids or
not a a good functioning education
system enriches life for
everybody because the people that emerge
in this education system enrich the
world right which in turn enriches
everyone's life so you know
it's a no-brainer as far as i'm
concerned education is the is the silver
bullet you fix that
you get absolutely everything else for
free so
uh yeah it's it's and the other person
is a retired teacher which i also think
is almost perfect because you're not in
it
right you're not like oh my job's
dependent on you there's no education
three people or i'm one of those three
people well i think you should
you should find people's perfect number
right
the host and the the the fire started of
it right
so for you to be like that i know well i
think i'm getting an idea of what you
like to like to have conversations then
you probably like to run off and have
more conversations but you don't want to
be tied to one specific thing
right a little bit right that seems to
me what's happening yeah yeah well this
is what
this is what i've seen right so i think
for them right for you to be the kind of
starter of it
right and have three so there's three
there
and then get them together get them
talking to each other
and then each week right go along and
have the conversation with them
and then as a as a kind of like
in it but observing it and taking note
of what you're saying because you've got
you've had probably had conversations
with hundreds and hundreds and hundreds
of people
right so then go back to the people that
you've had conversations that oh i
i'll go and ask them go and ask them and
then you can ask them
online without maybe not being in that
group
so you might have little groups of three
right so you have the little groups of
three so i think i think it would be
better
if if you could just um find a three
yourself
and be the one person that's kind of
interlinking them
because then you'll be able to see a
bigger picture of solutions that
from speaking people that you've spoke
to that
may not know these other three people
but it's important for you to have the
face-to-face meeting with the three
people
that you know of to start off with and
then
take it from there and let it grow out
from there instead of
mean one-on-one or together together get
them three together
can you uh do you would you be willing
to have a face-to-face meeting with the
three of them
well no nothing's face-to-face right now
face-to-face is zoom that's that's fine
right okay but i do think there's gonna
come a time when you're actually going
to need
to have people who can do the face to
face so you do the zoom and the online
and the digital
get them in the real on the outside i'm
just going to call it the outside world
for the want of a better word right
who are willing to meet face to face i'm
not one less
into for just my own personality even a
lot of the things i was like idea cafe
i'm gonna get people together it's just
not my thing but that being said the
people in my mind literally all live in
the same location
but i'm also picturing the people who
live first and are living
on farmland right
i kind of want them part of the like
it's like they have kids that are my
kids age and they're
this is very much relevant to what does
that look like homeschooling without
right i don't you want to have a limit
for me to for you to find the perfect
balance
of everything that you want to do
there's going to be an aspect of that
on online and offline right so there's
people who can't meet
for the digitally and zoom right so if
you want to start that with the zoom
and then as i said give people to watch
but you need a
an aspect of that where people are going
to meet face to face and you may find
if you get from the zoom there may be
people
from that zoo who want to meet face to
face and have discussions with and then
bring it back
you know what i mean so that you've not
seen or whatever but
you're you're providing right so say
like you're providing
the actual spark for the fire that's the
content the digital content which people
can go and watch
you may be in a location that they can't
get to right
so as i said if you if you go if you
find three online
and then from them three ask them would
they be willing
to set up a discussion group with three
people you know
face to face right and see see how that
goes as well you know what i mean
even that sounds like a lot of planning
to me just figure out the three
things are sparky and i'll see what i'll
see what fire starts and start the fire
okay you start the fight even that
minimal amount of money sounds like a
lot to me
i think i yeah i'm going to work in my
own chaos
okay let's take a bite of youtube we've
all got our